Connecticut Pomological Society Records
© 2005 University of Connecticut
Connecticut Pomological Society Records.
1894-1992.
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center.
Connecticut Pomological Society.
4 linear feet.
MSS19980347
In February 1891, a group of sixteen peach growers under the leadership of the Secretary of Agriculture, Theodore S. Gold, met in the State Capitol to talk about the formation of a fruit society. In December of that same year, forty growers met and elected John Smith of New Britain as president. Since its founding, the Connecticut Pomological Society has been involved in development of pest management and disease control for Connecticut's orchards.
History
In February 1891, a group of sixteen peach growers under the leadership of the Secretary of Agriculture, Theodore S. Gold, met in the State Capitol to talk about the formation of a fruit society. In December of that same year, forty growers met and elected John Smith of New Britain, CT, as president. J.H. Hale of South Glastonbury, CT, who claimed to be the first commercial fruit grower in the country, was present at all these meeting but did not serve as the president of the society until 1895. Nonetheless, Hale was surely one of the prime movers of the organization. At the end of the nineteenth and beginning of the twentieth century, growers, acting on the advice of men like J.H. Hale, had interplanted apples in peach orchards. These apples began to produce in the early 'teens.
Since its founding, the Connecticut Pomological Society has been involved in development of pest management and disease control for Connecticut's orchards.
(Historical information from Histories of Connecticut Orchards.)
Scope and Content
the collection includes materials relating to the preparation of a video tape and two booklets about apple growing in Connecticut, as part of a grant to commemorate the 100th anniversary of the Connecticut Pomological Society. The collection was assembled by Lucy McTeer Brusic, and most of the notes and and manuscripts in the collection are her notes pertaining to the completion of these various grant projects.
The first part of the collection consists of research notes and photocopied articles collected in support of the video and booklet project. Some print materials and sporadic copies of the proceedings of the Connecticut Pomological Society are included here as a well. Box 2 begins with a series of slide photographs of apple orchards, and moves on to a series of oral history transcripts. The rest of the collection consists of audio cassettes, video tapes, and miscellaneous index cards.
Arrangement
Series I: Project mateials (undated, 1894-1991) contains publications, photocopies, and personal notes. The booklet prepared as part of the grant is near the beginning of this series.
Series II: Slides (undated, ca. 1900-1991) consists of photographic slides associated with the project.
Series III: Oral Histories (1989) features several interview transcripts prepared as part of the grant project. Audio tapes are available in the audio visual materials for most of these interviews.
Series IV: Audio Visual materials (undated, 1938-1989) including a copy of the video tape which was the end product of the grant project.
Series V: Ephemera (undated) contains Lucy Brusic's index card notes.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to various aspects of Connecticut history. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Separated Material
The following materials have been separated from the collection and cataloged:
Bountiful Century Dodd Video 120
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Subjects:
Fruit-culture—United States.; Fruit-culture—Connecticut.; Fruit trade—Connecticut.; Apples.; Plant diseases.; Fruit Diseases and pests—Connecticut.; Connecticut Societies, etc.—Agriculture.; Storrs (Conn.)—Societies, etc.—Agriculture.
Document Types:
Correspondence.; Typescripts.; Transcripts.; Notes.; Publications.; Photographs.; Videocassettes.; Audio visual materials.; Fliers. [printed matter]
Restrictions on Access
There are no access restrictions on this collection.
Acquisition Information
Materials donated to Dodd Research Center by Lucy Brusic. Many of the color slides are credited to Ray Gomes. Entire project sponsored by NEH, Connecticut Historical Society, and Connecticut Humanities Council grants.
Detailed Description
- Series I: Project Materials, undated, 1894-1991
  - Apple Exhibit Brochure, 1991 (Box 1:, Folder 1)
  - “Histories of Connecticut Orchards” Booklet, 1990; (2 copies) (Box 1:, Folder 2)
  - Various draft printouts, including apple variety data, ca. 1989 (Box 1:, Folder 3)
  - Project research notes and photocopied articles, ca. 1894-1989 (Box 1:, Folder 4)
  - Project notes, including notes on folklore, ca. 1989 (Box 1:, Folder 5)
  - Copied articles on apple growing (pertaining to pre-1900), ca. 1900-1989 (Box 1:, Folder 6)
  - Copied articles on apple growing, 1900-1920 (Box 1:, Folder 7)
  - Materials donated by Jack Rollins, including notes on effects of 1938 hurricane on apple growing, 1913-1960 (Box 1:, Folder 8)
  - “The Inside Story of the Apple” pamphlet donated by Henry Buell, 1927 (Box 1:, Folder 9)
  - Copied articles on apple growing, 1920-1940 (Box 1:, Folder 10)
  - Copied articles on apple growing, 1940-1960 (Box 1:, Folder 11)
  - Copied articles on apple growing, 1960-1980 (Box 1:, Folder 12)
  - Copied articles on apple growing, 1980-1990 (Box 1:, Folder 13)
  - American Fruit Grower magazine, 1980, 1991; 2 issues (Box 1:, Folder 14)
  - Clippings relating to pesticides, ca. 1988-1992 (Box 1:, Folder 15)
  - Pesticide publications, 1978-1985 (Box 1:, Folder 16)
  - Pesticide newsletters and publications, ca. 1987-1989 (Box 1:, Folder 17)
  - Pomology Ephemera (pamphlets, fruit-sorting guides), 1914-1948 (Box 1:, Folder 18)
  - Proceedings of the Connecticut Pomological Society, 1912-1913 (Box 1:, Folder 19)
  - Proceedings of the Connecticut Pomological Society, 1914-1916 (Box 1:, Folder 20)
  - Proceedings of the Connecticut Pomological Society, 1935, 1945 (Box 1:, Folder 21)
  - Proceedings of the Connecticut Pomological Society, 1966-1968 (Box 1:, Folder 22)
  - Proceedings of the Connecticut Pomological Society, 1987-1990 (Box 1:, Folder 23)
  - New England Fruit Meetings, 1985, 1987, 1988 (Box 1:, Folder 24)
  - New England Fruit Meetings, 1989-1990 (Box 1:, Folder 25)
- Series II: Slides and Photographs of Apple Orchards, undated, ca. 1900-1991
  - Slides grouped by donor, ca. 1900-1989 (Box 2:, Folder 26)
  - Slides by Ray Gomes, 1989 (Box 2:, Folder 27-29)
  - “Best of” older slides, with related caption text file, ca. 1900-1970, 1989 (Box 2:, Folder 30)
  - Color photos of Buell Orchards and Lewis Farms, undated (Box 2:, Folder 31)
    [Box 2 also contains three unnumbered boxes of photos. One box is labelled “Bug slides from CAES”, another is from the National Apple Museum in Gettysburg. The third box is not labeled, but the individual slides appear to be related to others in the collection.]
- Series III: Oral History Transcripts, 1989; NOTE: These transcripts were made by Lucy Brusic for her grant project, and are in no way affiliated with the Department of Oral History at the University of Connecticut. The files do not contain official release statements from the persons interviewed. Any researcher wishing to re-publish this material would need to contact the subjects for specific permission to do so.
  - John Buell and Orrin Bishop interview transcript and support materials, ca. 1989 (Box 2:, Folder 32)
  - Lewis and Ethel Hurlbut interview transcript and support materials, 1989 march (Box 2:, Folder 33)
  - John Lyman interview transcript and support materials, 1989 April (Box 2:, Folder 34)
  - [No audio tape available - no tape made]
  - Gene Bishop interview transcript and support materials, 1989 May (Box 2:, Folder 35)
  - Bud Rogers interview transcript and support materials, 1989 May (Box 2:, Folder 36)
  - Hawley Rising interview transcript and support materials, 1989 May (Box 2:, Folder 37)
  - Robert Josephy interview transcript and support materials, 1989 August (Box 2:, Folder 38)
  - Norman Barnes interview transcript and support materials, 1989 September (Box 2:, Folder 39)
  - Charles Henry Young interview transcript and support materials, 1989 October (Box 2:, Folder 40)
  - Stew Ramsey interview materials (no transcript made), ca. 1989 (Box 2:, Folder 41)
  - Notes by Brusic regarding Jack Rollins interview, ca. 1990 (Box 2:, Folder 42)
  - Transcript of radio interview from circa 1973, 1973, 1989 (Box 2:, Folder 43)
- Series IV: Audio and Visual Materials, undated, 1938-1989
  This material has only been loosely organized.
  - Audio cassettes pertaining to the oral history interviews are grouped together in one container. The second container contains assorted audio cassettes relating to the collection, including a program about the Connecticut Pomological Society's 'Man of the Year' from 1961, Jack Lyman, as well as secondary copies of some of the interview tapes. (Box 2)
  - Includes a film master of “A Bountiful Century: Fruit Growing in Connecticut, 1891-1991” as well as a video copy of this same work. Other various tapes are included that were used as source material for the video project, including footage of damage from the 1938 hurricane. (Box 3)
- Series V: Note Cards, undated
  - A large shoebox of note cards was prepared by Brusic and arranged by topica. The cards are apparently keyed to various issues of the Proceedings of the Connecticut Pomological Society. There is a smaller bundle of notecards, also from Brusic, apparently keyed to the subject of apples and humor. (Box 3)